<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word from the Lord unto all the faithlesse generation of the vvorld, who know not the truth, but live in their own imaginations; with a true declaration of the true faith, and in what it doth differ from the worlds imagination: written in obedience to the Lord, that al may see what faith is owned by the saints, and what faith is denied. And also a few words unto all professors of the world, who worship not the true God, but their own imaginations and conceivings instead of the true God: also a call from God unto all the the world to repentance, that all may turn unto him, lest the Lord destroy both root and branch of them that repent not. Also a few words unto you that scorne Quaking and trembling, which all the holy men of God witnessed that spake forth the Scripture, and also the holy men of God justified, and all you denied that scorneth such as witness such things now, as ever was in all the generations of the saints. With a word to those that are called Anabaptists, Independants, Presbyterians, Leve</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825745</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825745</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40325)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1793:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word from the Lord unto all the faithlesse generation of the vvorld, who know not the truth, but live in their own imaginations; with a true declaration of the true faith, and in what it doth differ from the worlds imagination: written in obedience to the Lord, that al may see what faith is owned by the saints, and what faith is denied. And also a few words unto all professors of the world, who worship not the true God, but their own imaginations and conceivings instead of the true God: also a call from God unto all the the world to repentance, that all may turn unto him, lest the Lord destroy both root and branch of them that repent not. Also a few words unto you that scorne Quaking and trembling, which all the holy men of God witnessed that spake forth the Scripture, and also the holy men of God justified, and all you denied that scorneth such as witness such things now, as ever was in all the generations of the saints. With a word to those that are called Anabaptists, Independants, Presbyterians, Leve</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30132:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Word from the Lord, Vnto all the faithleſſe Generation of the VVorld, who know not the Truth, but live in their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations; with a true Declaration of the true faith, and in what it doth differ from the Worlds imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: written in obedience to the Lord, that al may ſee what faith is owned by the Saints, and what faith is denied.</p>
            <p>And alſo a few words unto all Profeſſors of the World, who worſhip not the true God, but their own imaginations and conceivings inſtead of the true God: Alſo a Call from God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the World to Repentance, that all may turn unto him, leſt the Lord deſtroy both Root and Branch of them that repent not.</p>
            <p>Alſo a few words unto you that ſcorne Quaking and Trembling, which all the holy men of God witneſſed that ſpake forth the Scripture, and alſo the holy men of God juſtified, and all you denied that ſcorneth ſuch as witneſs ſuch things now, as ever was in all the Generations of the Saints.</p>
            <p>With a word to thoſe that are called Anabaptiſts, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants, Presbyterians, Levellers, and Ranters, that they may turne to the Lord, by yielding obedience to the light in their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>By thoſe whom the World knowes by the names of <hi>George Fox, &amp; James Nailor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30132:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30132:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To all the faithleſſe generation of the world, and to all who deſire to know what faith and hope we live in and what faith and hope we deny.</head>
            <p>THat Faith wee owne and witneſs, is that which ſtands in Jeſus Chriſt in the everlaſting Covenant of light,<note place="margin">John. 1.9.</note> who is the light of the world and hath enlightened every one that cometh into the world, and this light we believe and follow, and by this are we led out of all the waies, works, and worſhips,<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.12</note> of this darke world, and the effect of this light we witneſs by faith. And by this faith we deny all who ſay this light is not ſufficient without the teaching of man to guide in all the waies of God, and all ſuch we deny,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.4.5. Tim. 4.5.</note> for thoſe are they who knowe not the voice of Chriſt, and therefore here a ſtranger and hireling who heap up teachers having itching eares who cannot indure ſound doctrine, and in this Chriſt we believe, who is our life and Salvation; and all them and their faith we deny, who ſay they have faith, and their lives is not the life of Chriſt, but live in ſin, and worldly pleaſures, and ſay they cannot be ſaved from their ſins in this world, but in part, and this faith we deny and them,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.8. Heb. 7.25. 1. Timo. 1.9.</note> for theſe deny the end of Chriſts coming in the fleſh who cannot believe he is able to ſave to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all that come unto him, and this faith is reprobate, and theſe deny the Lord that bought them, and have made ſhiprack of faith and a good conſcience and makes the blood of Chriſt of no effect to them who are not cleanſed by it, and all them and their faith we deny who ſay they believe and know the will of God, but they have not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.4.16.</note> for that Chriſt in which we believe is the great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God unto Salvation in all that believe, and who hath this Chriſt hath power, and in him we have power to do the will of God, but theſe are they that know not Chriſt nor his power,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5.</note> but run into notions and forms but deny the power, and from ſuch we turn away, for ſuch
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30132:3"/>
know not him in them who is greater then he that is in the world, but are wi ling to ſerve ſin and be led Captive at the divells will, not minding the light and power of Chriſt to be guided by it, and then would ſeeme to caſt the fault on God, as though he had given a Chriſt that was not able to ſet free til after death, &amp; theſe put him to open ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e whoſe faith &amp; profeſſion we deny,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.17. Rom. 1.22. Rom. 10 3.4.</note> &amp; we deny all who ſay they have faith in Chriſt, and yet their righteouſneſs is not perfect, but this faith we witneſs which receives the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God, even the free gift of righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt, and this is perfect which is the righteouſneſs of faith, and all who have not this righteouſneſs are in the falſe righteouſneſs which is not perfect, and theſe are ſhort of the righteouſneſs of God, and would eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſs, and theſe are the Boaſters who would juſtify themſelves and diſpiſe others,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.27.</note> but by the righteouſneſs of faith is boaſting excluded, and heer is no juſtifying of ſelfe, but denying ſelfe and ſelfe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs &amp; exalting the righteouſneſs of God, which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect which is in Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.9. Phil. 1.11.</note> who is made unto us righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs &amp; ſanctification, &amp; by this faith we deny all who ſay they have Chriſt, and have not this righteouſneſs, but whoſe righteouſneſs is unperfect, and that Chriſt and that righteouſneſs we deny which is not perfect, and witneſs that Chriſt in which we are made the righteouſneſs of God, and this Chriſt is our righteouſneſs and perfection, and this faith we owne and witneſs, which is not a talke of faith, as the worlds profeſſors, who ſay they have faith but are dead in ſin and cannot witneſs the work of God in them,<note place="margin">Jam. 2.26. Eph. 2.10. 1. Iohn. 5.4. Gal. 1.4..</note> but that faith we owne which is lively by which the work of God is witneſſed in us working out ſin, and by which we are his workmanſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, and this is our faith by which we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world, and the Divell, and all you we deny who have a profeſſion in the world, and in whom the works of the Divell are brought forth, and their faith and hope we deny who ſay they hope to be ſaved but live in ſin making a profeſſion, and this is the hope of the hypocrite
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30132:3"/>
which ſhall perriſh, and not the hope of Chriſt, for he that hath this hope of Chriſt purifies himſelfe even as he is pure,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.3. Heb. 6.19</note> and this faith and hope we owne which purifies the heart and enters into the place of holineſs within the vaile, but that which is without holineſs, we deny which is not in Chriſt, but in a vaine mind,<note place="margin">Ro. 10.8.</note> and we deny all who ſay they have faith and Chriſt, and yet their word and light is without them, and that word we witneſs which is nigh in the heart, and this is the word of faith, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preached, and he that hath Chriſt or faith, hath this word, which is Chriſt the light not in letter but in ſpirit, and all them we deny whoſe law is without and morrall, and that law we witneſs which is ſpirituall written in the heart, and this law is perfect and endures for ever,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.10.11. Heb. 7.19.</note> and all the Changeable laws wee deny, and all whoſe Law is without we ſee to be in the old Covenant of works, which made nothing perfect, and the ſelfe righteouſneſs which is filthy raggs, and by the light of Chriſt are we convinced of that righteouſneſs not to be of faith, therfore whoſe faith and works ſtand here, them we deny and ſee them all worſhipping without the new covenant in the oldneſs of the letter, whoſe law is without,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13. 1. Cor. 14.13.</note> their light without, their Church, without, their Baptiſme, prayers, and Singings without, their Chriſt without, their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs without, and ſo their faith without, all which we witneſs to be within, and within we worſhip in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit, and by this ſpirit we do ſee all that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God and his righteouſneſs, to be in the world, and ſtrangers to the covenant of grace,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.23.24.</note> and that faith and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, we deny and God denies, who ſeeks ſuch worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers as worſhip in ſpirit and truth, and this faith and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we owne not knowne to the world, and therefore hated.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:30132:4"/>
            <head>To all the Worlds Profeſſors and People, that you may ſee where you are and Repent.</head>
            <p>THe word of God is not known to the world, nor worldly wiſedome; hee that hath the word hath life, hee that knowes the word knowes God, and heeres life manifeſt, and the word hath quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him and rayſed him out of death and dead workes, he that hath but the letter heareth the ſound, but knowes not where or what it is, and as he received it in the aire, hee declares it, and death ſpeakes light words without power, and dead workes and lightneſs is brought forth, and the power of death raines, and the life of that is but an imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and not the life it ſelfe, the chaffe but not the graines toſſed in the wind, and the Prince of the aire is fed and ruleth, and here vanity is exalted, the light mind is fed with airie notions, would be wiſe but the colt is at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not ſubject to the yoke but kicks againſt the pure, and the obedience is not, and the croſs is deſpiſed, but the nature who feeds heere whoſe end is for deſtruction and for the fire, for the nature knowes not the living word but the letter, and is without God in the world, but hee who hath the word hath God and is come into the Covenant by which all things ſtand, for he is come into the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the fall to the firſt fruites, and witneſſeth the word ſpirituall, inviſible, powerfull, pure, and ſharpe, a divider and diſcerner by it he is ſanctified and made clean, by it he is eſtabliſhed and unmooveable and is fed daily, it is his life, his joy and delight, and the word is not to fetch from above nor from below neither is it to ſeeke it in a chapter or a ſteeplehouſe without, but it is nigh in the heart, and in the mouth, by which word he is kept at all ſeaſons, it is his counſeller &amp; he inquires at it, as at an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and thereby he is brought to live the life of Godlineſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30132:4"/>
and from which is ſpoken words of life and power to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and hee ſpeakes not his owne words, nor brings forth his owne workes: but hath ceaſed from his owne workes as God did from his and is entred into his reſt, and is come into the eternall Sabboth, and is comprehended into the word which is Chriſt, and is no more his owne, for now Chriſt ſpeakes in him, acts in him, and workes in him the will and the deed; now Chriſt and hee is one married to him, and Chriſt is his head and husband, and now the head ſpeakes prayeth and prayſeth, and propheſies, and is uncovered and heere is the Church of the firſt borne the pillar and ground of truth, where the woman muſt bee covered and kept ſilent and is not to ſpeake in the Church, is not to uſurpe authority, but is to be in ſubjection, and if ſhee would know any thing let her ask of her husband at home, and he is to her a covering of the eyes forever. Now all you Prieſts and People that talke of theſe things without you from the letter, this is a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to you and you reade the outſide in the letter and from that you imagine and ſo ſet up a forme or likeneſſe or i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of thoſe things, and here you worſhip, and for this you contend and would compell all to worſhip your image you have ſet up, and you goe about to perſecute and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all that will not worſhip and bow downe to it with you, but it is the forme you have, but not the ſubſtance, and you put the dead letter for the living word, and your meanings of it ariſing from the braines, and firſt wiſedom and naturall learning, thus you declare and call it prophecying and put off your hats which is carnall, but the head you know not, and it is the woman that ſpeakes and the head is covered, and ſo you dishonour your head and honour your ſelves, neither are you ſubject to your head, but your owne will rules in you, and you live in the pleaſures of the world, and are become wanton, and have ſet your eyes upon many lovers, and you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterated from your husband nor live not with him, nor is he a covering to you neither can you witneſs him in you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30132:5"/>
nor you in him, nor the pure ſeed of God is not brought forth in you, but the ſeed that is accurſed, neither is the pure language brought forth in you, but as to God you are ſmitten with barrenneſs and brings forth nothing but words, windes, ſhewes and ſhadowes, imitations, inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, imaginations and conceptions, and you never looke to bring forth better fruit, never come to holyneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and your firſt fruits, and that eſtate wherein you were created, and you will not know you are departed from your firſt fruitfullneſs, and have loſt him in whom your life ſtands, and in whom your fruits is found, and are become widdowes, and deſolate as to your firſt hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and have been running after other lovers, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping under every greene tree, and the holy fleſh is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from you, and you are doting upon the Egyptian and the Aſſyrian for wiſedom and ſtrength, whoſe fleſh is as the fleſh of horſes, and have been as fed hoſes living in the luſt of the fleſh as it is at this day.</p>
            <p>Now all people ſtand ſtill a while and ſee from whence you are fallen, and the cauſe of all your unfruitfulneſs and returne to your firſt husband from whence you are fallen, that you may bring forth your firſt fruits; for till then all you doe is abomination to the Lord, and he cannot accept it, for what you bring forth is the ſeed of the adulterer and of the whore, a generation of evill doers, and yet you make a profeſſion in out ſide as to righteouſneſs and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but the power is to act righteousneſs, you have not but in your actions brought forth but the image of the Devill, for all ſin beares his image, and hee is the father of it, let no man deceive you thorough faire words, hee that ſins is of the Devill, and is doing his worke, and upon this image where it is, the wrath of God is revealed from heaven in flames of fire, here is your portion you workers of iniquity.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30132:5"/>
            <p>THe word of the Lord God to all you that ſcorne trembling and quaking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſcoffe at them, and ſcorn at them, and throw ſtones at them who own trembling and quaking, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ere that you might be ſeen to bee ſtrangers from all the Apoſtles and Prophets in the generation that ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, mocked them then in that age, and thoſe ages and thoſe times, but now yee are the ſcoffers that are come in the laſt times whom they ſpoke of, bee yee witneſſes againſt your ſelves, to the light in all your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, I ſpeake, that with it you may ſee your ſelves to bee from the life of the holy men of God: <hi>Moſes</hi> who was a judge over all Iſraell, hee feared, trembled, and quiked, when the Lord ſayd unto him, I am the God of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the God of <hi>Jacob;</hi> then hee trembled and durſt not behold, at this which makes to tremble now: yee teachers and people ſcoffe at and ſcorne them now in your ſtreets, who witneſſe the power of the Lord. And <hi>Moſes</hi> forſooke the pleaſures of the world which hee might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed for a ſeaſon, hee might have beeene called the ſon of <hi>Pharahoes</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he refuſed it and forſooke <hi>Pharaoes</hi> houſe who was no vagabond.</p>
            <p>And <hi>David</hi> hee trembled, hee was mocked, they made ſongs on him, they wagged their heads at him, will you profeſſe <hi>Davids</hi> wordes, <hi>Moſes</hi> wordes, who are in the generation of your fathers, mockers, ſcoffers, wonderers, and deſpiſers, who are to periſh; Oh! bluſh and bee aſhamed of all your profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: <hi>Job</hi> trembled, and their fleſh trembled, and they mocked him, ſo doe you now where the ſame power of God is made manifeſt, and doe not you mocke and yet you profeſſe <hi>Jobs</hi> wordes? Oh! deceitfull Hypocrites, will yee not owne the Scripture, <hi>Solomon</hi> who was a King ſayd when the keepers of the houſe ſhall tremble and the ſtrong men of the houſe ſhould bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp; at this Prieſts &amp; Magiſtrates, and people ſcoffe at, where this power makes the keepers of the houſe to tremble, &amp; the ſtrong man to bow himſelfe, Oh! for ſhame never profeſſe <hi>Solomons</hi> words &amp; deny the power, for with it you are judged (with the power and life) <hi>Jeremiah</hi> hee ſhooke, his bones quaked, hee reeled too and fro like a drunken man, when hee ſaw the deceits of the Prieſts, and Prophets, who were turned from the way of God and they were not aſhamed, neither could they bluſh; ſuch were gone from the light, and ſuch were the women that ruled over the people, and hee was brought to cry oh fooliſh people who had eyes and could not ſee! they had eares and did not heare, that did not feare the Lord and tremble at his preſence who placed the ſands for the bounds of the Sea for a perpetuall decree, that the waves thereof cannot paſſe, and ſayd a horrible and filthy thing was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Land, the Prieſts bate rule by their meanes, and the Prophets prophecie falſly, ſhall not I viſite for theſe things ſaith the Lord? ſhall not my ſoule bee avenged upon ſuch a Nation as this? ſuch did not tremble at the word of the Lord, therefore he called them a fooliſh people, heare all yee the word of the Lord, yee fooliſh People who ſcorne trembing, and quaking, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30132:6"/>
quaking, and ſhaking; give over <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> wordes and making, a trade of them, for with his wordes yee are judged to bee among the ſcoffers and ſcorners, and ſtockers, for he was ſtocked by your generation, and ſo you ſtocke (who are the children of your fathers) them that tremble now at the word of the Lord, at the power of the mighty God, which rayſes up the ſeed of God out of the fall, and throwes downe the earth which hath kept it in the fall; ſo you that are in the fall where death raignes enemies of the truth, deſpiſing the power of God as ever your generation did; woe and miſery is your portion except you ſpeedily repent.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſayd heare yee the word of the Lord, all yee that tremble at his word, and ſaid, this is the man that God regards, that was of a broken and contrite heart &amp; tremble at his word, when their bretheren hated them, and perſecuted them, and caſt them out ſaying, let the Lord be glorified hee ſhall appeare to your glory but they ſhall be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Now to all ſcoffers &amp; ſcorners that deſpiſe trembling, you regard not the word of the Lord, they are not regarded with you that trembles at the word who are regarded of the Lord, therfore ye are contrary to <hi>Iſaiah</hi> his words, therfore never for ſhame profeſſe him nor his wordes, nor make a trade of his wordes, yee who ſeeke for your gaine from your quarter, yee greedy dumb doggs that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have enough, yee are they that deſpiſe trembling, you are they <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt who witneſſed trembling, and heere be you witneſſes againſt your ſelves, that with the light in your conſciences you may ſee you are out of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> words and are ſuch as hate them that tremble, that the Lord regards but ſuch you do not regard, but hate, and perſecute, mocke and rayle againſt, but it is manifeſt that you walke in the ſteps of your fathers who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Prophets, <hi>Habacuck</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, and <hi>Joel</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, blew the trumphet in Zion and let the inhabitants of the earth tremble, the people ſhall tremble, and all faces ſhall gather blackneſſe and the people ſhall be much pained, and now this trembling is witneſſed by the power of the Lord, this power of the Lord is come, the trumpet is ſounding the Devils are trembling, the earth is ſhaking, the dead is rayſing, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is prayſing God, and the world is rageing, and the ſcoffers are ſcorning, and them who witneſſe trembling and quaking, can ſcarce paſs up and down the ſtreets, but with ſtones, and blowes, and ſticks, and fiſts, or mocks or dogs, or reproches, and thus you vent forth your malice againſt them who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the power of the Lord, as the Prophets did, to come to the broken heart and contrice ſpirit, and tremble at the word of the Lord whom the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards them you ſtone, them you ſtocke, them you ſet your dogs at, and ſcoffe, and ſcorne, revile and reproach, but the reproaches are our riches, and prayſed bee the Lord who hath given us power above all, and if you ſee one as <hi>Habac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uck</hi> whoſe lips quivered, whoſe belly ſhooke, who ſaid rottenneſſe entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his bones, who trembled in himſelfe, if you ſee ſuch an one in this age now, you ſay he is bewitched, here again you ſhow your ſelves ſtrangers to that power, to that life that was in the Prophet, and ſo for ſhame never make a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30132:6"/>
of his words, nor a trade of his words nor of <hi>Joels</hi> who witneſſed trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, that which ye ſcoffe and ſcorne. Ye proud ſcoffers and ſcorners, ah! miſery miſery is your end, except you ſpeedily repent. And <hi>Daniel</hi> a ſervant of the moſt high God, he trembled, his ſtrength and his breath was gone, hee was impriſoned, hee was hated, he was perſecuted, they layd baites and ſnares for him, in whom the Holy Spirit of God was, now for ſhame all you that make a profeſſion of <hi>Daniels</hi> wordes, give over your profeſſion Prieſts and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who ſcoffes and ſcornes at trembling, with the light you are ſeene to bee out of <hi>Daniels</hi> life and by the ſame power, you are threſhed, for it you ſcorne and ſcoffe, and ſo heere againe bee witneſſe that you are ſcorners and ſcoffers againſt the truth, and with the Scripture you are judged to be contrary to the life of the holy men of God, and <hi>Paul</hi> a miniſter of God made by the will of God, a meſſenger of the Lord Jeſus, a veſſell of the Lord to cauſe his name to ſpread abroad in ſeverall Nations, when the darke blind world have got ſome of his words and epiſtles, and you filthy teachers make a trade of them and gets great ſummes of money for it, and ſo deſtroyes ſoules for diſhoneſt gaine, and making a trade of his wordes, and the reſt of the Apoſtles and Prophets and Chriſt, but denying that Spirit and life that they were guided by, and that power that ſhooke the fleſh and the earth which the Apoſtles witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed who ſaid when hee came among the Corinthians hee was then with them in weakneſſe, and feare and in much trembling, that their faith might not ſtand in the wiſedome of the world, but in the power of God, in that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which made him to tremble, at this power the world and all the ſcoffing teachers ſcoffe at in the townes, in your villages, in your aſſemblies, in your alehouſes, for ſhame lay away all your profeſſion of the Apoſtles wordes and conditions, and ſome ſcoffes at the power and call it of the Divell, and ſome perſecute them, ſtocke, ſtone, impriſon, and whip, in whom that power is made manifeſt, and loades them with reproaches as not to walke on the earth, the off-ſcowring of the world hated &amp; perſecuted, here you may ſee you are in the ſteps of your forefathers who perſecuted the Apoſtles and acted ſo againſt them, ſtocked them, mocked them, impriſoned them, ſtoned them, whipped them, hayled them out of the Synagogues, reproached them, ſhamefully intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, doe not you heere fulfill the Scripture and Chriſts ſayings, who ſayth if they kill you they thinke they doe good ſervice, and yet you make a profeſſion of Chriſts words, the Prophets and Apoſtles words, and calls your ſelves Churches and miniſters of the Goſpell; I command you and charge you in the preſence of the living God, to bee ſilent who acts ſuch things, ſcoffers and ſcorners, mind the light in your conſciences, which Chriſt hath enlightened you withall, that by it you may ſee your ſelves what you act and what you have acted, for who act ſuch things ſhall never inherit the Kingdoms of God, for all ſuch things with the light are condemned, and who come to witneſſe trembling and quaking, the powers of the earth to bee ſhaken, the luſtfull to come to be deſtroyed, the ſcorning and ſcoffing come to be iudged with the light in it, waite, to receive power, who ſhakes the earth,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30132:7"/>
this power wee owne and faith ſtands in it, which all the world ſcoffes at, the luſty ones, the proud ones, the preſumptuous ones, who live in preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet make a profeſſion of the Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pture as your Fathers the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes did, who were painted Serpents, and the Scribes who had the chiefeſt places in the aſſemblies, ſtood praying in the Synagogues, called of men Maſters, which Chriſt cryed woe againſt, who are not come ſo farr as the trembling of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vels, which believed and trembled, let that Judge you the light and life of the Scripture is ſeene and made manifeſt, that with it all you ſcoffers, and all you ſcorners, &amp; all perſecutors &amp; raylers are ſeen; take war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all yee powers of the earth how you perſecute them whom the world nicknames and calls Quakers, who dwells in the eternall power of God, left the hand of the Lord be turned againſt you, and yee be all cut off, and to you this is the word of God, to feare and to tremble and to take warning, for this is the man that the Lord doth regard, who trembles at his word, which you who are of the world, ſcoffes and ſcornes, ſtockes, perſecutes, impriſons, here you may ſee you are contrary to God, contrary to the Prophets, and are ſuch who hate what the Lord regards, whom wee owne, whom the world ſcornes; and cals Quakers, and ſet up that power, &amp; honour that power that makes the Devils to tremble, and ſhakes the earth and throwes downe the haughtineſſe of man, and which makes the beaſts of the field to tremble, and makes the Earth reele too and fro, and cleaves the Earth aſunder, and overturnes the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld, this power wee owne and honour and ſet up which the world ſcornfully calls Quakers; but all ſcoffers &amp; perſecutors and raylers, &amp; ſcorners, &amp; ſtockers and whippers, we deny with that power which throwes down all that nature, as ſeeing all who act ſuch things are for deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſhall never inherit the kingdom of God, ſo reioyce all yee righteous ones which are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake, for great is your reward in Heaven, reioyce yee that ſuffer for well doing, for yee ſhall not loſe your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and waite you in the light that you may grow up in the life that gave forth all the Scriptures that with it you may ſee all the Saints conditions, and with it you may ſee all that which they teſtified againſt, &amp; therwith it you wil ſee them that did reproach &amp; ſcoffe them &amp; mock them, &amp; perſecute them, &amp; whip them, &amp; ſtocke them, &amp; haile them out of the Synagogues, before magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſo to you who are in the ſame light &amp; life, the ſame things do they unto you now, that they may fil up the meaſure of their fathers, ſo with the light now they are ſeen to act where the light &amp; life &amp; power of God is made manifeſt, for as they did unto them, ſo ſhall they do unto you, &amp; heere is our joy and the Scripture fulfilled &amp; fulfilling, &amp; with the light which was before the world, which is now made manifeſt in the children of light, with it they ſee the world &amp; comprehends it, &amp; all things in it, &amp; the actions of it, &amp; with the light we ſee it to be for the fire, and all the works of it; for hee that loves it and turnes himſelfe from the light is an enemy to God, he turnes into wickedneſs for the whole world lies in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he turnes into the works of evill, who turns from the light, he is vvith the light, vvhich is of Chriſt teſtified againſt, &amp; to this light being made manifeſt, all the vvorkes of the vvorld are ſeen and made manifeſt, &amp; heere is joy and unity &amp; light, rejoyce in Trembling and rejoyce above all the vvorld.</p>
            <trailer>This is to goe amongſt the ſcattered ones, and amongſt all the vvorld.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30132:7"/>
            <head>A word to thoſe that are called Anabaptiſts, Independants, Presbyterians, Levellers, and Ranters.</head>
            <p>THe word of the Lord God to you, which are called Ranters, you had a pure convincement, I witneſs, which did convince you, but having fled the Croſſe, and now to it are become enemies, which turnes the grace of God into wantonneſs, and followes drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckenneſs, and curſed ſpeaking, ſporting your ſelves in the daytime, following oathes &amp; ſwearing, you never come into the Sons do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, had a convincement under the law, then ſtart up to be as Gods and never came thorough the Prophets, nor Moſes houſe, nor Chriſt who is the end of all oathes, for you that are in the oathes, and your drunckenneſs the law of God is caſt behinde your back, and you that are in your wantonneſs kill the juſt, and you that live in pleaſures are dead while you live, and you that ſweare are out of Chriſts doctrine, with the light which was before the world was, with it I do you comprehend, which is your eternall condemnation who be in the liberty of the fleſh in your hot burning luſts, but all ſuch are beggerly acted in that nature contrary to the light, and with the light to be condemned and to you this is the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And the word of the Lord to you who are called Levellers, you had a flaſh in your minde, a ſimplicitie, and your minds run into the earth and ſmothered it, and ſo got up into preſumption, and you would had unity and fellowſhip there, before life was raiſed up in you, ſo that withers, and much of it is withered as it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and with the light, that is condemned, in which light is the unity of both thoſe conditions.</p>
            <p>The word of the Lord to you who are called Anabaptiſts, you take up a command from the letter, and ſay Chriſt commands it which Chriſt did not, you command; but the letter commands it, you are not led with the light, which gave forth thoſe commands to obſerve them, but ſaith Chriſt hath commanded them in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, here you are them which uſe their tongues which the Scripture ſpeaks of, but I have not ſpoken to them ſaith the Lord, heer with the light you are comprehended, to be the witches which takes up
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30132:8"/>
commands as they did in the Galathians, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of which did bewitch them, who drawes from the ſpirit within them, to harken to your outward commands, them that did obſerve the commands was led by the ſpirit, and Chriſt bid them goe preach, he ſent them and bid them goe preach the Goſpel to every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they did not goe at the command of the letter, but at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, and they was led by the light which did compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the world, and the Prophets they did not goe becauſe other Prophets had gone and take their words, and make a trade of them nor uſed their tongues, and ſay he ſaid when the Lord had not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto them, but with the light they did them comprehend, and cry againſt, and the Lord bid them cry aloud and ſpare not, lift up their voyce like a trumpet, and ſhew them their ſins and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which walkt contrary to the light, with the light they are comprehended, &amp; all you who are turned from the light, and ſaith Chriſt ſaith ſo and ſo, and the Prophets and Apoſtles ſaid ſo in ſuch a Chapter and ſuch a verſe, and God ſaid ſo, and the command is in ſuch a Chapter and ſuch a verſe, here with the light you are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and ſeene to be them who uſe their tongues, and ſay he ſaith it, when the Lord never ſpoke to you, heer you are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with the light, and ſeene to be lyars, and are for the lake where all lyars muſt goe, and to you this is the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The word of the Lord God to you that are called Independants, your zeale it without the knowledge of God, with the life of God I beare you record that you depend upon your imaginations, you depend upon the letter, your minds are turned from the light of Chriſt within you, and that zeale and knowledge with the light which never changes, which comprehends the world with it, it ſhall be condemned, your knowledge, wiſedom and zeale: for the zeale, wiſedom, and knowledge which ſtands, is in the light, which condemnes that knowledg, wiſedom and zeale in that nature that acts contrary to the light, which changeth not, and to you this is the word of the Lord God, all your fruits will wither, and all your knowledg will periſh, and all your expectations and hopes will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, to you this is the word of the Lord God, no pillowes under your armeholes I ſow, but to the light in your conſciences I ſpeake, which will let you ſee your prayers and your praiſes, and all your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30132:8"/>
imaginations of the Saints words will wither, and is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem'd, to be froth, in the nature of the Sea, forming forth ſhame, I ſee come forth from you, with the eternall light which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the world, which light ſhall never change, with which light all your waies and actions is to be condemned, which light will teach you how to walke, if you love it, remember you are warned, in the time of your life, and to you this is the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The word of the Lord God to you, who are called Presbyterians, and to you who reade the common prayer, you are wholly in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs given up to it, and ſo your dark minds have the common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, and ſuch would have a King to reigne, for there is that nature that would have an earthly King to reigne, in which nature lodgeth the murtherer, deare deare is the love of God to all the world, in ſending his only begotten into the world, that whoſoever do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him ſhould not perriſh, but have everlaſting life. Who doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, and if you did owne the Son of God, you would owne the light which he hath enlightened you withall, then you would owne him to be Lord and King, and this light would lead you our of darkneſs, and from all your common prayers, and would teach you how to pray, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all your ſet forme of prayers, and ſet times, and this light will teach you how to pray, if you love it, there is your teacher, and if you hate it, there is your condemnation, when you are in the pit and in the lake, to the light in your conſciences, I ſpeake which Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened you withall, which is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation that hates it, and when you are in the Lake, Pit, and ditch remember you were warned in your life time, then all your common prayers, and all your ſet waies, and all your cuſtomary teachings, and all your private interpretations, and all your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Scripture, your Presbyterian forme, Independent, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſt, Ranter and Leveller, who are in any forms whatſoever, following your beggerly luſts of the world, with the light that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver changeth, you are ſeene, with the light, who lives in your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions turned from the light, and erred from the ſpirit and commands of God, all your profeſſion which hath not the life, will ſtand you in no ſtead, no more then the cheife Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſes, who was a ſeperated people: and no more then the Sadduces or any other
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30132:9"/>
which had not the life, when Chriſt came woe was the end of their profeſſion, who hath a profeſſion but hath not the life, with the light that comprehendeth the world, you are all ſeene which comes from Chriſt, who is the ſame to day, yeſterday, and forever, and changeth not, and to you all this is the word of the Lord God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 2. line 5. read Chriſt the</p>
            <p>Pag. 6. line 13. read graine</p>
            <p>Pag. 7. line 27. read braine</p>
            <p>Pag 8. line 17. read horſes</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30132:9"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
